Guide to the Curt von Faber du Faur Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Articles, Lectures, and Research Notes by Topic, 1946-1960; Series IV; 2.1; (5 boxes)
  - "Poeta vates," lecture in English, autograph draft, 19 p., with a related after-dinner speech in German, in a spiral notebook. The speech segues into remarks on Grimmelshausen. (Box 18, Folder 132)
  - "The problem of inspiration," autograph ms, 2 typescripts, and a version marked "Columbia Vortrag" (Box 18, Folder 133)
  - Renaissance. Notes and drafts (Box 18, Folder 134)
  - [Renaissance] "Gibt es eine deutsche Renaissance? Vortrag im Germanic Club, 27 January 1948," mixed autograph ms. and typescript (Box 18, Folder 135-136)
  - Reviews (Box 18, Folder 137)
  - Rilke, typescript. YUL Staff News, 1957 (Box 18, Folder 138)
  - "Rilke's letters to Kurt Wolff," autograph ms. YULG 24:3 (1950) (Box 18, Folder 139)
  - "Eine Sammlung deutscher Literatur des Barock in der Bibliothek der Yale-Universität in New Haven," 2 autograph drafts, typescript, and proof. Philobiblon 11:1 (1958) (Box 18, Folder 140)
  - "La Sorcellerie dans la littérature européene du XVIIe siècle," autograph ms. and typescript. Lecture for Yale Romance Languages Club (Box 18, Folder 141)
  - [Sporck, Franz Anton] Essay in English labeled "Über Sporcks Christliches Jahr in Versen," autograph manuscript (Box 18, Folder 142)
  - "Süddeutsche Stämme und Landschaften," autograph manuscript (Box 18, Folder 143)
  - "The three phases of German book illustration," autograph manuscript, typescript (Box 18, Folder 144)
  - "Voropitzische Lyriker," autograph notes in a composition book (Box 18, Folder 145)
  - [Weigand] "Rede zu Hermann Weigands 65. Geburtstag," autograph draft, 2 typescripts. Monatshefte 50 (1958) (Box 18, Folder 146)
  - [Werfel] "Ten poems of Franz Werfel," autograph ms. in German, typescript in English. YULG 25:3 (1951) (Box 18, Folder 147)
  - [Wolff] "Die neuere deutsche Literatur in Briefen an Kurt Wolff," autograph ms. English version, YULG 23:1 (1948) (Box 18, Folder 148)
  - [Wolfskehl] "Karl Wolfskehl,"autograph and typescript. Printed version, Deutsche Beiträge (Box 18, Folder 149)
  - "Der Wunschzettel," autograph ms., 6 p., on collecting and desiderata, annotated by H. S. Dejon (Box 18, Folder 150)
- Correspondence, 1937-1964; Series V; 0.42; (1 box)
  Most of Faber's correspondence retained by the library is part of the Yale Collection of German Literature office correspondence. A small group of letters is filed here, including a few with Martin Bircher, Victor Hammer, Alma Mahler-Werfel (one letter from her, 1 July 1950), the writer Joachim Seyppel (who was then teaching at Bryn Mawr), the baroque literature scholar Marian Szyrocki, Peter Viereck, and Kurt Wolff, among others. A large file of letters and third-person correspondence documents Faber's activity as an officer of the Modern Language Association. In the mid-1950s, he served variously as secretary and chairman of that organization's German III section and later as a member of its Advisory & Nominating Committee.
  - Letters, A-Z by writer, 1937-1964 (Box 19, Folder 151)
  - Bircher, Martin, 1960-1961 (Box 19, Folder 152)
  - Hammer, Victor, 1952 (Box 19, Folder 153)
  - Liepe, Wolfgang, [circa 1958] (Box 19, Folder 153a)
    Negative microfilm copy of a collection of letters to Liepe congratulating him on his 70th birthday in 1958
    Includes letter in the form of a poem from Curt von Faber du Faur, page 17
  - Modern Language Association, 1948-1964 (Box 19, Folder 154)
- Personal papers, 1940s-1997; Series VI; 1.25; (6 boxes, 9 folders)
  The Thacher family history materials were brought to the library by Jan Thacher (son of Doris); there is related correspondence in the YCGL correspondence file from the spring of 1997. Doris Thacher's maternal grandfather, Friedrich Cotta von Cottendorf (died 1951), was the brother of Curt von Faber du Faur's mother, making Doris Curt's first cousin once removed. The description of Mrs. Thacher's collection contains information on the Faber du Faur family chairs: two from the set are still in the Beinecke Library.
  The personal papers also contain a few clippings about Faber's wife and stepchildren. Emma Faber du Faur, née Mock, was first married to Rufus W. Blake, many years her senior, who made a great deal of money as an executive of the Sterling Piano Company in Derby, Connecticut. Rufus's suicide in 1901 left Emma a wealthy widow. Her second husband was a German, Paul Schabert. The children of that marriage were Kyrill and Beatrice ("Bibi"). Kyrill was one of the founders of Pantheon Books—another link between Faber and Kurt Wolff. Bibi ("die einzige Dame der Welt, die wir haben," as recalled by Yale Professor Peter Demetz) hosted a well-remembered literary salon on Whitney Avenue in New Haven in the 1950s before moving to Italy. The various web sites devoted to Titanic survivors constitute an usual source of information about Emma: she appears there as Emma Schabert, traveling in the company of her brother, Philip Mock, who was at the time an official of the Sterling Piano Company.
  The personal papers also include a ledger that records how Faber built his collection between 1912 and 1939. Subsequent lists and a card file document the collector's growing focus on the seventeenth-century.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Boxes 26 and 27 (audiovisual material). Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Contact Access Services for further information.
  - "Anschaffung der Bücher in der Faber du Faur Sammlung 1912-1939.", circa 1940s (Box 20, Folder 155)
    Record of his book purchases, by accession number, with prices and running totals of prices and number of volumes. Bound ledger listing 3412 titles.
  - "Deutsche Litteratur von 1500 – 1870. Original-Ausgaben." (Box 20, Folder 156)
    Alphabetical list of the collection, keyed by accession number to the preceding ledger, with fuller descriptions of the books. Bound in red leather.
  - "Manuscript Catalogue of the Emma and Curt von Faber du Faur Collection.", 1940s-1950s (Box 20, Folder 157)
    Typed list of the collection, organized by literary eras. Bound in library buckram.
  - "Barock." Card file of the collection, ca. 1494-1740., 1940s-1950s (Box 21, Folder 158)
    These and the following card files give fuller information on the books than the previous three lists and are often the only source of provenance information; the cards are keyed by accession number to the 1912-1939 list. Although much of the material in the card files appears to predate Faber's arrival at Yale, it also contains cards for books transferred from the Yale library stacks into the Yale Collection of German Literature; these usually cite the old Yale call number.
  - "1740-1890." Card file of the collection, with some special sections at the end of the file, including "Italienische Reisen 1600-1870.", 1950s (Box 22, Folder 159)
  - "1740-1890." Card file of the collection, with some special sections at the end of the file, including "Italienische Reisen 1600-1870." (continued), 1950s (Box 23, Folder 160)
  - Thacher, Doris von Schmeling. The Cottas, their portraits, paintings, memorabilia and my remembrances. Photocopied memoir., 1997 (Box 24, Folder 161)
  - Thacher, Jan. The Cotta Legacy: the Doris von Schmeling Thacher Collection. (Beacon, N.Y, no date), 1997; YCGLMSS23_0001; 1; 00:14:10; The audio is low. The copy YCGLMSS23_0002 is of better quality. (Box 26)
    A printed note is attached. It reads: I must [appoligise] for the quality of this copy, the older of my 2 VCRs is unfortunately at the end of its useful life. However the audio track is reasonably good and along with the visuals in catalogue will give you the Idea. I intend to beg, [barrow], hopefully not steal another deck and make some acceptable [copy's] and will replace this copy with one of those, this will take a while and I wanted to get this off to you. Jan
    Restricted fragile material.
  - Thacher, Jan. The Cotta Legacy: the Doris von Schmeling Thacher Collection. (Beacon, N.Y, no date), YCGLMSS23_0002; 1; 00:43:03; This is a better copy than YCGLMSS23_0001. (Box 27)
  - Family: clippings and ephemera, 1975 (Box 24, Folder 163)
  - Seventieth birthday; production and acquisition of the oil portrait by Mark Potter, 1960 (Box 24, Folder 164)
    The portrait has the Beinecke Library art inventory number 1960.24.
  - Honors: Yale Medal, 1964; Order of Merit, Federal Republic of Germany, 1965 (Box 24, Folder 165)
  - Photographs, 1960 (Box 24, Folder 166)
  - Obituaries and condolence letters, 1966 (Box 24, Folder 167)
  - Private library list and appraisal by Laurence Gomme, 1966 (Box 24, Folder 168)
  - Biographical information from Internationales Germanistenlexikon (offprint) (Box 24, Folder 169)
- Writings by Others, circa 1950s; Series VII; 3
  - Closs, August. "Priebsch-Closs Collection," carbon typescript, ca. 50 p., bibliography of books from a collection now at the University of London, School of Advanced Studies, Germanic Studies Library (Box 24, Folder 170)
  - Faber du Faur, Moriz von. "Damals, gestern und heute," series of articles, Stuttgarter Zeitung, 1953 January 6-March 12, photocopy (Box 24, Folder 170a)
  - Jaszi, Andrew Oscar. "Hofmannsthals Erlebnis der Zeit: Anmerkungen zum Unterschied zwischen der Sprache der Prosa und der Sprache der Lyrik," typescript, 12 p., annotated by Faber (Box 25, Folder 171)
    Also includes: Marcuse, Ludwig. "Freuds Aesthetik," carbon typescript, 31 p., removed from MLA correspondence
  - Panish, Paul. "Gottfried Finckelthaus," typescript, 11 p. (Box 25, Folder 172)
    Also includes: Seyppel, Joachim H. "Freedom and the mystical union in Der Cherubinische Wandersmann," typescript, 27 p. plus notes, with a 1-page abstract and a shorter German version. Removed from MLA correspondence
  - Catalog cards (Box 25, Folder 172a)
    Catalog cards from a Yale Collection of German Literature shelflist for classifications Zg16 and Zg 17